[Music]
thank you for joining us today Mr Wayne
okay I appreciate the opportunity so how
are you doing today reasonably well nice
comfortable cool so uh I did a little
bit of research uh on you prior to this
interview and um I think one quote that
really spoke out to me was um I I think
it was an end Gadget interview and I
think at the end of that you asked them
oh is my life really that interesting
and then and then I think you ended that
with you know he talked about your
experience at Apple and stuff like that
and you said oh man I'm I'm a footnote
in you know somebody else's history uh
it's I really have that belief in the
back of my head that I will be a
footnote in history because I happen to
have known someone yes do does it does
it bother you that you know a lot of
these interviews are you know based on
your you know small time at Apple and
your relationships with Steve Jobs and
does it bother me no does it like annoy
you in any way another one of these just
look I I I live my life step by step
event by event as it happens and by the
way I count myself extremely fortunate
to have been at a turning point in
history and that establishment of Apple
was indeed a turning point in history
although at the time of course nobody
ever knows this right it takes a
perspective of History to do that like
like you said um after you left uh apple
and Atari um you concluded your career
at a 16year stin with as a chief
engineer at a it was part of my
engineering life but some years later I
went to work for it was 1982 I went to
work for uh Thor Electronics in Selenas
California uh the first project I did
there was really something that appealed
to my sense of humor uh I was asked to
design and build a brand new slot
machine which I did took there uh uh no
no
unfortunately uh I had been 10 years out
of the business when they asked me to
design a machine for them and uh they
were getting all set to license up and
and and get us to produce these
machines uh but in that 10 years the
entire industry had changed so much so
that the rules of the game in the gaming
industry in Nevada had changed to such
an extent that neither my employer nor I
really wanted to be a part of it when
they established uh legalized gambling
in 1931 in Nevada why because what was
in the state it was San fleas and hila
monsters it was a middle of a depression
and Nevada had already been in a
depression so what were they going to do
to uh get some life into the state so
they hit upon two laws one they reduce
the the uh residency requirement to six
weeks somebody could come here and get a
divorce okay fine what are you going to
do for six weeks oh well we'll legalize
gambling
well um there was a lot of gambling
going on in the country most almost all
of it illegal which meant that machines
were gaffed that uh you couldn't trust
the roulette wheels and all the rest of
it and they wanted to make damn sure
that people would understand gambling in
the v would be absolutely straight and
above board and they uh the gaming
commission would be a mediator between
casinos and players and neither was to
to cheat the other that was the rules of
the game game but the basic rule of
equipment gaming equipment was that the
player shall not be deceived into
believing he's playing against one set
of odds when in fact he's playing
against a different set of odds well
slot machines were built that's way you
had three reels 20 pictures on each reel
one chance and 8,000 of hitting the 3
sevens okay everybody knew this no
problem well the new gaming commission
Rules by the time I'd finished my
machine was the microprocessor based
slot machine where I won't get into the
mechanics of why they went through this
but they had an electronic reel inside
rather than the Reel spinning and
stopping at random and then the machine
looks at the reels and say what are you
is it a winner how much do I owe you uh
instead they had an electronic reel that
did the spinning and it came to a stop
and told the reels where to stop well
that's okay too except that they figured
they could get much bigger rewards if
they had more than 8,000
combinations so with the virtual real
system which is what that's called uh
they went to 256 stops per real so the
player is looking at a machine with
mechanical reels thinking he's playing
against one in 8,000 odds and he's
playing against odds in the millions
they're dealing the game in the back
room and come out and say you lose I
mean this uh as far as I was concerned
it was the same as the gaft machines
that uh were cheating people throughout
the uh the 20s and 30s I wanted to talk
to you about the patents you own I mean
you the patents that that you own um you
know from what I understand you you
you've developed you know dozens and
dozens of them and well about I have
about a dozen patents which one um which
one are you most passionate about and
because I know you've taken a few to
court and a few notable companies too um
I have never instituted legal action on
my patents okay uh because as you'll
read in my book insolence of office uh
there's a section in there on patent
law and patent law in the United States
is not the same as it is in the rest of
the world in the rest of the world if
you are in England and uh you come up
with an automotive device that's worth a
fortune to a
manufacturer and it's infringed by
British
Leland um you wouldn't take Leland to
court you would go to your nearest
Corner friendly neighborhood
constabulary and swear out a criminal
complaint for patent infringements and
the officers of British Leland would
find them themselves in a criminal court
answering a criminal action that's the
difference in the United States it is
not a crime to infringe on a patent
which means as it says on the cover of
every one of my patents I've got the
right to defend myself for the next 17
years against GE Borg Warner westing
house whoever goes into court against me
and any attorney will tell you whoever
goes into court with the most money it's
like guy whoever goes into a poker game
with the most money is virtually
guaranteed to win Pat law has become the
property of corporate entities the
independent inventor is virtually
non-existent in the United States he has
no standing in law and no way to defend
his invention in short if you ever come
up with the greatest invention in modern
history the best thing you could do is
to lay down with a cold Toler on your
head until the feeling passes because
you'll never realize anything out of it
so I I remember when I emailed you for
the interview and you responded back
with um you kind of summarized your
entrepreneurial Adventures you know
throughout your life as uh being either
a day late and or a dollar short oh yeah
and you know well you don't regret like
no no leaving apple and everything you
know a lot of a lot of unlucky things
has happened to you like for example
selling the uh the original I guess
agreements between oh yeah the contract
that that's the one thing in this whole
experience I really do regret I sold
that contract for
$500 that was 20 years ago that was the
same contract that sold at auction about
18 months ago for 1.3 million that I
regret okay but even on top of that I
mean like it's I I I think uh you even
had some of your life savings stolen
from a safe too I lost my life savings
in the Florida house that uh was what
obliged me to sell the house in Florida
uh it was an inside job okay we'll leave
with that and the person who stole it
was caught spent six years in prison
which did me of course a lot of good uh
okay but there was 145 ounces of gold uh
$3,000 face value in Silver Coin and how
much collector's coin I will never know
that's do you ever like kind of like sit
by yourself and go like why me no as a
matter of fact it kind of confused
people at the
time um the the Fon not only broke into
my safe
by finding the combination and going in
because the safe is 5 feet high four
feet wide 3 feet deep weighs two and a
half tons the walls are 4 in thck
concrete and steel he needed the
combination to get in
there uh and what he did was he turned
it over to some pros because he had been
shoving stuff up his nose and apparently
they threatened him with you know
concrete shoes if he didn't uh come up
with the money so he decided to pay him
off with my money so he told them when I
was going to be out of the house and
they came in and emptied the safe and
then they smashed the lock took me two
days to get the lock open to get the
safe open and I was waiting wondering
hoping uh well they opened the safe and
of course it was
empty and everybody was wondering why at
that point in time I did not go
screaming up the
walls and my answer to them was very
simple and I meant it I said what am I
supposed to do make myself sick over it
Ides I mean the situation has happened
I'll deal with it when something happens
you just deal with it is that kind of
how you dealt with you know any problem
that you know anything that's happened
to you even in the corporate world you
know working of course oh yes I was
telling you about patent law okay I had
a patent uh in
1972 on a device that had many uh uh
consequences consequential products one
of them was the first Improvement in in
electrical meter movements in 150 years
I don't know if you're familiar with a
darsonval meter movement you certainly
don't know it by that name but you are
familiar with electric pointer meters
okay that was the darsonval meter was
invented in the
1850s and that's the same meter they
build today it's got three basic
technical problems it's called hunt lag
and hysteresis well I came that patent
that I had in
1972 one of its applications was a meter
with no hunt no lag and no hysteresis it
was the first Improvement in direct
reading electric meters analog meters in
150 years I I sent as soon as I got my
patent I had built a prototype of this
meter I wrote uh letters to all the
major meter manufacturers triplet and
Simpson and GE and Hoy and fastron and
all of them half of the people I wrote
to never even bothered to answer my
letter most of the other people uh came
back and said well you'll sign this
disclaimer we'll be happy to look at
your patent okay in other words sign
away your rights and then they'll go
ahead and let you know whether or not
they're interested okay I did wind up
with a president of Simpson in my office
oh and thought boy here it is I finally
made it all right and I showed him the
meter demonstrated it to him he was very
impressed and listen very attentively to
what I was
saying and then said uh Mr Wayne how
would you like a job I said I've got my
own Corporation here what do I a job for
well we were hoping that maybe you'd
come to work for us in Simpson and
Chicago we'll give you laboratory
facilities and everything you want and
by the way you'll bring your patent
along too won't you so this is the sort
of thing I've been up against all my
life so I wanted to talk a little bit
about um apple and you you've answered
it many times of you know why you left
it wasn't because of you know passion
you know you just didn't want to um
you just weren't sure like how long it
was going to take for this for yeah you
haven't hit it
yet I read a lot of different reasons
there were there are were many reasons
for why I took myself out of it 12 days
later one of the reasons it was a
straightforward business decision in the
sense that I had had my own Corporation
as I told you years
before and that was where I learned that
I was a hell of a lot better engineer
than I was a
businessman and uh the whole thing went
Belly Up and rather than use the
corporate shell to protect myself
against creditors and so on which is
what you normally do that's what you
build a corporate shell for uh I felt
that it was my Enterprise it had failed
because of my inability to do the job
right I had it I blew it why should
everybody else pay for it because I blew
it so all the creditors over over a span
of about a year were paid off 100 cents
on the dollar and all the stock that I
had sold in that Corporation was bought
back at the price they paid for it and I
felt very good I could look in a mirror
when I was shaving and not be
embarrassed all right but at the same
time it was a very traumatic
experience well with that reality in
mind uh all of a sudden I I'm in this
company arrangement corporations
company and who is
reachable I mean jobs and W didn't have
two nickels to rub together I had a
house I had a car I had a checking
account I was
reachable well when that contract was
drawn up jobs went out and did exactly
what he was supposed to do he got a
contract with a place called The Bite
shop to sell them a certain number of
computers and then he went out also and
did exactly what he was supposed to do
and he borrowed
$115,000 for the materials necessary to
fill the order perfectly
appropriate the only problem was as I
heard the bite shop had a terrible
reputation for not paying their bills if
this thing blew
up how was that $115,000 going to get
repaid did they have the money no was I
reachable yes among other things when I
jobs and I worked at Atari I went to
work for Atari the company was three and
a half years old and Atari was
organized uh Under The Genius of a man
by the name of Nolan Nolan Bushnell okay
well Nolan being the genius that he was
pursued exactly the same course that
Geniuses do when they go into business
like this get the product out on the
street what it takes to set up a company
is a nuisance all right right uh you
want to set up a drawing number system
fine your first drawing is drawing
number one next drawing is drawing
number two it doesn't work that way not
when you had been in engineering and
design and drafting for the number of
decades that I had you had to have a
meaningful numbering system so that the
documents that you put into the files
were traceable you could pick up one
document and follow the thread of
numbers to rebuild the entire paper
structure for that particular product
and you do this through the structuring
of your numbering system so I had to
rebuild the numbering system jobs knew
about these documentation systems that I
had put together for Atari and he was
very impressed with them and I had every
reason to believe that jobs wanted me in
apple to set up and run their
documentation systems their
documentation
Department well there was a bit of a
problem there because I was a product
development engineer of my own right
even though I knew at the time that I
was standing in the shadow of Giants all
right I knew these guys knew a hell of a
lot more about product development than
I did I felt I was never going to get a
project of my own they would certainly
never get involved in slot machines
which was my passion and the last thing
I wanted to do was to spend the next 20
years of my life in a large backro
office shuffling papers these were some
of the reasons aside from the fact that
I I was in my 40s and these kids were in
their 20s and they were whirlwinds it
was like having a tiger by the tail and
uh I said this many times before and I
meant it if I had stayed with apple I
probably would have wound up the richest
man in the cemetery now if you were the
same age as them would that have changed
your decision of course absolutely
because my whole world view would have
been different 20 years before I mean as
I say I was in my 40s so I'd had quite a
bit of life's experiences and quite a
bit of formulated ideas of my own as to
what I saw for myself were um was a
young Steve and you know were they both
like relatively you know Risk Takers you
would say oh absolutely definitely I
mean just to do what I just described to
you was a risk right all right but that
was uh let me put it to you this way the
entire Apple Enterprise from then to the
time he passed on was Steve
Jobs you may recall that when Steve Jobs
was running the Enterprise it was very
successful he got into an altercation
with his board of directors in which he
lost and he left the Enterprise and from
there it took a huge
dip and it wasn't going to come back
again until Steve Jobs came back again
that's got to tell you something
now what sort of a personality did it
take to do what jobs
did personality okay if you had your
choice between Steve Jobs and an ice
cube you'd nuzzle up to the Ice Cube for
warmth all
right uh he had me come in to help him
work out a fairly simple dispute with
Steve
wnc because he himself was not that much
of a diplomatist
and he thought that I could do it I'm
the adult in the room okay and I worked
it out wasak was a reasonable fell all
he' do is lay it out for him he could
understand H that job's position was
correct in that dispute and that was
it uh so that was fine but that wasn't
jobs jobs was not a
diplomatist jobs was a sort of a fellow
that played people like pieces on a
chessboard and he was very serious ious
about what he did and he had every
reason to believe that he was absolutely
right which meant that if your view was
different than his you better have a
damn good case to present you said he
was a ruthless businessman I think oh
very absolutely to even at that young
age he was even at that young age you
want the last place you ever wanted to
be was between him and any place he
wanted to get to you'd wind up with
footprints on your forehead I mean this
is the sort of a guy he was I had one
altercation with him after some years
after uh Apple had gotten
started and uh something he wanted me to
do he came to see me and he wanted me to
do this and I didn't feel that it was
right and I think I was one of the few
people in the world that said no to
him I don't think he liked it including
saying no to his offer for you to come
back too oh he three times he offered me
a positioned at Apple during the years
that followed uh the founding he's very
adamant about it too if oh yeah he was
very strong about it but I I said no
this is you got your world I got my
world and that's the way it wanted to
be but
um uh he had I've been working for a
company uh called LTD I think it was and
uh it was a guy who had developed a chip
that made it possible
for uh uh a touch switch to be expanded
into a touch
potentiometer and you do this on your
iPhones and so on right now you slide
your finger along the screen and you get
the pictures to move and so on well I
had I worked for the guy who had uh had
the original patent on those chips that
did
this and jobs wanted me to talk the guy
into selling his company to uh to Apple
and I said no I wouldn't do that and I
said I would talk to the guy about
licensing the technology to Apple
exclusively no other computer company
would have it but I would not encourage
the guy to sell his company I mean
that's all the guy had that was it that
was the whole
thing uh I have to admit today that
probably my decision in that was wrong
not in the sense that I was wrong in my
philosophical concept I was wrong in not
giving the man the choice to make for
himself and and in that sense I was
wrong in that decision he came to me at
the
beginning and he was telling me about
this situation that he had with dnak
wasak had developed this personal
computer circuit and they wanted to
found a
company uh but there were other things
that he wanted to do things that were
more interesting and he wanted my
opinion should he
proceed and I said well that computer
that you're talking about is undoubtedly
going to be a very successful product
and whatever it is you want to do you
can do it a hell of a lot more easily
with money in your pocket and so I would
if I were you I'd go ahead and do it you
know and uh well in that sense he took
my advice along with probably 50 other
people's advice and and went ahead and
did it but I also told him at the same
time I said look one of the pitfalls you
have to watch
for is
Success when you have made a lot of
money don't forget what you wanted the
money
for he
forgot I had the distinct
impression that it may have been making
money at the beginning but not very long
into the
Enterprise it was the Enterprise itself
it was the game that drove
him uh the money was incidental although
he was not very
open-handed uh when it came to
money uh but nonetheless I don't think
it was making money that drove him I
think it was the game itself so out of
all the things you've done in in your
life and you you reflect what would be
um the proudest thing that you've done
that you remember the most that depends
on what category we're talking about um
would be the first thing that pops into
your head the first thing that pops into
my had in terms of
accomplishments of which I've had
relatively few absolutely glorious
successes um when I uh when I was
working for um Thor electronics and uh I
had designed their slot machine and then
the company and I both decided that's
not what we wanted to do so they made me
chief
engineer um because among other things
they had a problem to
solve uh linten Data Systems had come up
with a field computer one of these
little bricks went into military
application and it had many many many
possible uses so it came to me to
develop the entire product solve the
problem and come up with a brand new
product and design it and make it work
even sometimes in a few cases machine
some of the bits and pieces that went
into it and that's the product I'm
proudest of doesn't mean anything I mean
that product matter was was Obsolete and
out of use along with its uh uh
companion
equipment 20 years ago 15 years ago
right uh but it was still my product I
did it right from scratch that's amazing
yeah so my last question is actually
comes from Twitter and uh I and the
person wants you to tell a story about
Steve Jobs that you have not told before
I had a a stab store in uh Tucson
Arizona and I got a phone call from from
Steve Jobs Direct hadn't happened before
hi Steve how you doing he says look I
haven't got a whole lot of time uh look
there will be airline tickets waiting
for you at the airport and uh My
Chauffeur will pick you up when you get
here uh at San Jose and uh uh we'll set
you up at no San Francisco because they
set me up at the Mark
Hopkins and I said what's this all about
he says well we're doing a presentation
I thought nice of you joined us okay
fine and so I'm wondering what the heck
this is all about what's going on here
because Steve this is not this is out of
character for Steve
Jobs um but anyway okay so I get on the
plane pick up the airport set me up in
the hotel the next morning his people
come in and pick me up and take me down
to the auditorium where they're doing a
presentation on the G3 I think it was or
something like that the new uh they were
presenting among other things their new
uh Apple computer the one that was a
transparent shell with the blue lights
inside iMac okay iMac right anyway he
did his Spiel on stage and afterwards he
comes gets me and go to the back and you
know there's a bouet and coffee and
sandwiches or whatever and um then we
took the tour of the convention and uh
we jump in the car and we go off to the
Apple facility
where uh Steve wnc joins us and and the
cafeteria had lunch and we're sitting
around this table out on the patio
carrying on
this conversation about absolutely
nothing small talk and then it's uh
that's it have a good trip back and
we'll see you and I'm thinking to myself
what the heck was this all about and I I
never was able in my life to find out
what the heck it was all about it was
was very anticlimactic at the end
because I'm I'm on the plane going home
think it must have been something he had
in mind what did he do this for I you
can understand and you don't know until
I still do not know to this day what
that was all about that's funny wow well
thank you so much for taking the time
today I appreciate it well it's been a
pleasure I assure you thank
you